[lighthearted music playing]
[plane engines roaring]
[lighthearted music continues]
[music stops]
["Take Five" playing]
[narrator] It was late at night,
and there was hardly anyone
in the terminal.
My mother saw a photograph of Liz Taylor
in an upcoming movie
called The V.I.P.s.
She wanted a coat just like it,
except she bought hers
from a church basement sale
where all the wealthy people
sold their secondhand clothes.
- Goodbye, Grandma.
- Goodbye, sweetheart.
- Mwah. [chuckles]
- I'll miss you.
- Mmm. Goodbye, Mom.
- Mmm.
Goodbye, honey.
- [PA system dings]
- Final call for Trans World Airlines,
Flight 700 Royal Ambassador
Super Jet service to London.
Now boarding at Gate 3.
All aboard, please.
[narrator] The voice over the PA system
seemed so sophisticated.
I imagined it belonged
to someone really beautiful,
more like an actress of some sort.
Maybe if I act like Marilyn Monroe,
the ticket agent will put us
in first class. [chuckles]
[narrator] She also said
that all the drinks were on the house
if you flew that way.
Of course I didn't really care,
as long we really got to go.
["Breakfast At Tiffany's" playing]
[announcer on PA]
Trans World Airlines, Flight 393
Super Constellation service to Pittsburgh,
Dayton, Chicago, Kansas City,
Denver and Los Angeles.
Now boarding at the West Arcade.
All aboard, please.
[narrator]
The excitement ran through my body
like something I had never felt before.
Knowing that, within minutes,
I would be airborne for the first time
was comparable to nothing,
including playing doctor
with the kids on the block.
And that was saying
a lot for an eight-year-old.
I remember everything about that night.
The lights being dim in the terminal,
color of the airline insignia
as we moved quickly
to the gate in the West Arcade.
Even my mother seemed excited,
but for totally different reasons,
I'm sure.
Probably something like
the free drinks that she could have,
or the potential for meeting
a handsome man on the plane.
My mother was about 49 years old,
and quite attractive.
Blue eyes, nice hair,
and a good figure for her age,
she told me.
She would even have had a better figure
if she hadn't had me so late in life.
And a lot of men didn't mind
a little bit of a potbelly.
It was very sexy to some, she thought.
Maybe she'd fall in love
with someone really cool,
like the captain of the plane
or something.
Rushing through the Idlewild airport
was so much fun.
I couldn't believe we were really,
actually going to fly this time.
Most of our visits to the airport
were to see people off.
One time my mother actually
had to fly to go to work
in some play that she was doing
in summer stock.
But this time I would get to go.
[triumphant music playing]
[wind gusts]
[narrator] It all seemed very surreal.
Now my heart was in my throat.
Everything seemed
as if it were in slow motion.
She was beautiful.
Silver and white,
with two red accent stripes
and the letters TWA printed on the side.
Oh, what a sight.
The wind blew cold in my face,
but it couldn't interrupt my first love.
Noble in appearance,
strong and powerful in impression.
This would begin an experience
I would never forget.
As we climbed the steps
to board the aircraft,
I noticed something very peculiar.
There wasn't very many people
boarding with us.
Only a few really.
Then I pretended that the flight
was really only for me and my mother,
and wasn't that unique?
Welcome aboard. It's much warmer in here.
[narrator] The stewardess at the top
of the stairs was tall and slim
and had a warm smile.
[triumphant music continues]
[music ends]
So we also have an emergency map for you.
[narrator] There was something
different about her.
Something that was hard to pinpoint.
Later my mother would get
to know her quite well.
Almost best friends.
I did ask her why Liz seemed
so different from others,
and my mom told me that it was
because she had depth
and true sadness in her life
from being in a concentration camp.
[plane engines starting]
[narrator] As the engines started,
one at a time,
I sat in what seemed like a big,
soft, comfortable chair.
I could hardly hear them at all.
Big propellers turned around as
fire exited through the backside exhausts.
I knew it was the jet age,
but there was something exciting
about being in an aircraft
that would take twice as long
to get there as a jet would,
especially my first time.
I remember I saved my coins
in a black floral purse.
Your grandmother, my mother,
gave me this floral purse
to save money in it.
And now you should save money in it,
and then maybe we can go
on a short trip together.
We could go to Philadelphia, Hartford.
We could go to Boston!
Yes. [chuckles]
There was nothing like it when my mother
got excited about something.
The whole world seemed to
have brightness and hope.
["Samba De Uma Nota Só" playing]
- [volume decreases]
- [exhales] Okay.
[inhales deeply] Okay.
I was gonna keep this a surprise,
but we are moving to Los Angeles.
Real… Really?
[giggling]
There's a director friend of mine
from the Allentown Playhouse
who has promised if we get ourselves
out west by February,
he is going to get me some work in a film.
For real?
I can't believe it.
[sniffs, giggles]
[narrator] Mom already
had quite a few jobs
as an extra under her belt,
so it didn't seem that far-fetched.
She also taught drama in school,
and prior to that had
a full-time stage career.
And when she wasn't working,
I was her best audience.
I'll be right back.
I gotta go check my schedules right away.
[narrator] I practically
flew upstairs to my room,
where I had my airline schedules.
United, American, TWA.
There it is.
"Propeller One-Way Night Coach.
$95 full fare, children half fare."
That's it!
Now back to flight times.
"Trans World Airlines, Flight 393
departs Idlewild airport at 9:00 p.m.
Super Constellation services
to Los Angeles
with intermittent stops at Pittsburgh,
Dayton, Chicago, Kansas City,
Denver and Los Angeles.
Arrives at 3:00 p.m. the next day."
[TV announcer] Only Trans World Airlines
links 70 cities in the USA
with 15 world centers overseas.
[singers on TV]
♪ Nationwide, worldwide ♪
[TV announcer] Depend on…
[singers on TV] ♪ TWA ♪
♪ TWA's the way ♪
["Wives and Lovers" playing]
[narrator] By the time I came back down,
the lights were off in the living room.
And the music from the radio portion
of the stereo was playing softly,
"Wives and Lovers," sung by Jack Jones.
Her cigarette was burning in the dark,
a glass of white wine by her side.
Then I worried that what she said
about moving to Los Angeles
might not be true.
Maybe just a daydream of hers.
Oh, well.
I thought I could still save
for the short trip.
Maybe I'll…
I'll look at my schedules again.
[song fades]
[narrator] My grandmother had
a '57 Plymouth Belvedere.
So there we were, in December of 1962,
on our way to Idlewild Airport
with Flight 393 on my mind.
When are we gonna get there?
[Grandma] Honey, when-when
the odometer gets to 62,
we'll be there.
[narrator] Now it was fun
to see the big billboards
boasting different opportunities
that one could take, like,
"Fly Pan Am, seven hours to Paris."
Or "TWA, the best way to California."
And here I am on this plane
going to one of the farthest trips
the airline offers.
There were a total of about 15 people
on this first segment of the flight.
I was wearing a hunter's cap
that I forgot to remove,
probably due to coming in from the cold.
Nevertheless, on takeoff,
this was my look.
I could tell that my mother
was excited for me,
but for the moment was kind of
impatiently waiting to be airborne
so she could have
a cigarette and her drink.
[engines sputtering]
[narrator] I really enjoyed watching the
fire come out of the back of the engines.
The in-flight magazine would tell you
that for a propeller engine,
that was typical.
["Come Fly With Me" playing]
♪ Come fly with me ♪
♪ Let's fly, let's fly away ♪
♪ If you can use some exotic booze ♪
♪ There's a bar in far Bombay… ♪
[narrator] As we sped down the runway,
that surreal feeling came over me again.
And at that moment,
the aircraft left the ground.
- I can't believe I'm flying.
- Hmm.
[narrator] My mother
looked straight ahead,
and then she turned and smiled at me.
I'll always remember my mother that way.
- [song ends]
- [engines roaring]
The takeoff was much more gentle
in feeling than I thought it would be.
For some reason, everything
that happened thus far that night
seemed perfect.
For years, no matter what
negative experience I might have,
from the time
I would leave for the airport
until the time I would arrive
at my destination,
life would seem safe,
and I would be happy.
[engines roaring]
[narrator] My mother liked Manhattans,
but I liked Coca Colas.
Liz showed up by the side of our seats.
Now what can I get you to drink?
- Can I have a Coke?
- Sure.
- I would love a Manhattan.
- Of course.
And is it okay to smoke now?
Of course, yes.
[narrator] Newport filter cigarettes.
That turquoise box,
that half-moon in the middle of it,
would always bring to mind
pleasurable moments.
As she lights up,
that first satisfying breath of smoke
leaves her mouth
and I would think, "How festive."
All my mom's friends
from the theater smoked.
As a matter of fact,
I don't remember an adult who didn't.
I could see every star in the night sky.
["So Many Stars" playing]
Or so it seemed
as I looked out the window.
"This is so beautiful.
Why don't people just live in airplanes?"
I started to reflect on how sometimes
at home, late at night,
I would lie in bed awake,
listening to the drone of some airplane
flying over the house,
probably having just left Newark
or LaGuardia airport.
And I would think,
"Where is that plane going this late?
Who's on it?
And are they sleeping?
Are there beds on board?"
And here I am,
maybe even on that very same plane
that I had been pondering.
The gentleman in seat 3D
wants you to have this drink on him.
Oh, how nice of him.
Oh, please thank him for me.
[narrator] When my mother
wanted to impress someone,
often her voice got deeper and richer.
I called it her theatrical voice.
She didn't like it when I'd say it,
but it never stopped her from using it.
Shortly after, almost like clockwork,
the most handsome gentleman,
about 50-years-old,
sat across from us in the same aisle.
My mother at once wondered if this indeed
was the gentleman
who had treated us to the drink.
[passenger] Do you mind
if I sit next to you?
If you don't, I'll pull you over.
I'm terribly nervous about flying.
You are not.
Don't contradict me.
- But you're not, Mom.
- [chuckles]
Honey, why don't you go up to the cockpit
and meet some of the pilots?
[narrator] Actually, that was a good idea,
even though I thought
I was probably in trouble.
So I left my mother to her own devices.
I was halfway to the cockpit when I saw
what seemed to be the most bizarre sight.
Hello. I'm the ten-foot-tall man.
Would you like my autograph?
Who?
I work for Barnum and Bailey Circus.
I'm the ten-foot-tall man.
Okay.
[narrator] In the early '60s,
the cockpit doors were not locked,
and one could have easy access to them,
usually with permission
from the stewardess.
Liz was not to be found,
so I opened the door
to the cockpit anyway.
There were three men facing forward,
so they didn't see me enter.
- Tell me, was she not beautiful?
- I mean, she was gorgeous.
You know, I just can't believe
that she did that with all of us.
- I know.
- I can.
[narrator] I only caught part
of the story one was telling.
Only later did I realize,
when I was older,
that they were probably referring
to sex or something.
[chattering]
Whoa.
Hey, are you, uh…
Are you going to Pittsburgh tonight?
No, Los Angeles.
[chuckles]
How did you end up on the milk run?
I wanted to stay on the plane
as long as possible,
but my mom can't afford a nonstop jet.
[narrator] I thought they would've loved
the idea that I liked planes so much,
but they saw the more
inconvenient side of it, I guess.
Okay, okay.
Well, we're only with you until Chicago.
So, you know, if and when you get bored,
you're more than welcome to come up.
Just do make sure you ask
the stewardess next time, okay?
Sure.
Thank you.
What's the ten-foot-tall man?
Oh. That's your new girlfriend.
[narrator] Nevertheless, I was flying,
and all night at that.
Could life be any better?
By the time I got back to my seat,
Mom was on her second drink
and already getting very touchy
with her new friend Harry.
This is my baby boy, Jeff.
- Hi, Jeff.
- Hey.
This is Harry.
Harry's from Pittsburgh, honey.
He is a lawyer.
And he knows
some of the Pittsburgh Steelers.
Isn't that wild? [chuckles]
Are you married? Do you have any children?
Why, yes, I am. I have a boy and a girl.
Oh. That's good.
[chuckling]
["Last Tango In Paris" playing]
Hope you like chicken.
I like fried chicken.
Well, it's just like it.
It's called chicken cordon bleu,
and it's very tasty.
Okay. I'll have some.
[narrator] When I got back to my seat,
Harry was whispering something
in my mother's ear.
I waited until I thought he was through
so I wouldn't get in trouble.
[mother chuckles]
Oh, what a wonderful man.
So well-spoken.
[narrator]
My mother liked people who spoke well
and enunciated words and were articulate.
She didn't like accents
too much on people,
unless they were using them for a role.
She said good speech reflected
how well educated they were.
Her friend Julia was a beautiful woman,
very wealthy, married to a rich inventor,
and seemed to have it all,
except my mother
could never get over the idea
that she had a thick New Jersey accent.
She would say, "What a shame.
All that beauty and wealth,
and that horrible New Jersey accent."
The funny thing is that sometimes
Mom would actually have
the same kind of accent herself.
If we're ever in Pittsburgh, honey,
Harry would love to take us to dinner.
Oh, with his wife and kids?
Smart-ass.
[chuckles]
[narrator] As the darkness of the night
turned into snow clouds
outside the window,
I could sense something
being placed before me.
[Liz] This is for you.
[narrator] And from the smell of it,
it was chicken cordon bleu.
Wow. It really did look
like fried chicken, but better.
I started to dig in.
Oh, oh, oh.
I like chicken, and I like cheese.
But I'm not sure I can eat them together.
Mom, I don't really like this.
Can I have another Coke?
Oh, sure, honey.
[engines roaring]
[narrator] As we started our descent
into the Pittsburgh area,
I could finally see outside our window.
We were below the cloud layer now,
and it was snowing at a pretty good rate.
It actually looked quite beautiful
to see the city below,
kind of glistening through the weather.
Then I started to think that possibly
there was some child down below
in some house,
listening to the drone
of the engines above
and wondering,
"Who's on that plane so late?
And where are they going?
And were they sleeping or not?"
["Peaceful Lullaby" playing]
[narrator] We could hardly
feel the landing, it was so smooth.
[narrator] The blue lights
that lined the taxiway
seemed to stand out even more in the snow.
As we taxied up to the gate,
an announcement over the PA system
of the plane was being made.
[on PA] This is your captain speaking.
Due to the unexpected snowstorm,
those of you continuing on
to Dayton and Chicago
will be delayed until further notice.
Please check with the ticket agent
at the gate for further information.
[Liz] Not to worry.
TWA will be taking care
of the hotel for the passengers.
- Free of charge. Okay.
- Thank you.
So we will have a hotel room?
- Yes. Don't worry.
- Great.
Okay.
[Jeff] I asked the man behind the counter
when the hotel was built.
He told me 1952.
[narrator] Now I could fantasize
about all the people
that had to do
the same thing we were doing
in the middle of the night since 1952.
Okay, sweetheart.
So the airline will call
when the flight's gonna be ready,
but that won't be for a couple of hours.
So, you should try to get some sleep.
- Okay?
- All right.
I'm gonna go down to
the lounge for a nightcap.
All right.
- Okay. You good?
- Yep.
- Okay. I love you.
- I love you too.
[narrator] Somehow I knew
Harry was gonna be involved,
but I held my tongue.
[lighthearted music playing]
[phone rings]
Hello?
Yes, we'll be there.
[narrator] I ran out the door,
I flew down the hallway,
and I pushed the elevator button
over and over again.
[mother chuckles] No, you need to stop.
Mom! Mom, come on!
We're gonna miss our plane!
[mother chuckles, kisses]
Mom, come on!
The plane leaves in 20 minutes!
We're gonna miss it!
[narrator] As I looked down the hall,
I saw Mom leave some different room.
Coming.
It didn't really matter,
even if she was with Harry.
What really mattered was
that we only had 20 minutes
to get to the gate to continue our flight.
For 3:00 in the morning,
my mother was in an awfully good mood.
But so was I.
Three hours of sleep
and the rest of our journey to go.
The flight from Pittsburgh to Dayton
was just under an hour,
and was far more interesting
in retrospect.
I watched my mother go through
more emotions in 40 minutes
than I had ever seen before.
- [chuckling]
- What could she be telling her?
Later, of course,
I got the whole story on Liz.
- [Liz] I don't remember a lot…
- Mm-hmm.
…other than being confused by it.
But I was only nine years old
when we tried to flee the country,
and my brother and I were
the only ones to make it.
And, unfortunately, we had to
watch them taking our parents away.
Oh, honey.
No, I-I'm okay. I'm okay.
I've gotten through this.
[narrator] There was a TV show
in the New York area at the time
called Remember Us.
It showed actual footage
of the Nazi event.
It was probably more responsible
for my nightmares than anything.
I just always felt bad for Liz.
Anyway, my mother really cared for her.
It was almost as if someone
who had more emotional pain than her
offered some kind of relief.
I was suddenly sorry I hadn't gotten
to know the ten-foot-tall man.
At least I would've had
someone to talk to.
But tonight I would join
the evening stars.
["Quiet Nights of Quiet Stars" playing]
♪ Quiet nights of quiet stars ♪
♪ Quiet chords from my guitar ♪
♪ Floating on the silence
That surrounds us ♪
[narrator] We decided to stay on board
during the stop in Dayton.
Mom and I had actually got a nap in.
We were in the air again
before we awakened.
Liz let us sleep
as long as we were buckled in.
No one had gotten on in Dayton.
Well, anyone that seemed that interesting.
At 4:00 in the morning, why would they?
So we slept until Chicago.
It was still dark when we arrived
in the somewhat new O'Hare terminal.
It's my last stop.
It's my home base.
But I have planned a couple
of surprises for you.
[inhales deeply]
I've arranged for you both
to fly first class
- to Kansas City and Denver.
- [mother gasps]
And another little surprise
will be waiting for you in Denver.
[chuckles] So…
[whispers indistinctly]
So here are the details.
Just give this to the ticket agent.
- Okay?
- Thank you.
- All right. Goodbye.
[narrator] All I could think about was
how much it would have cost us
if we had to pay first class ourselves.
It was something like $185 one way.
The amount of toys
and hot dogs I could buy.
And that's including probably
two or three more trips like this.
What a gal, that Liz.
Suddenly, my mother's
whole demeanor changed.
I could see the visible change
come over her.
Her posture was straight,
her chin up, her walk was noble.
We were flying first class.
And she was an actress flying
to the West Coast, first class.
I know that she was wishing
that she had worn that fake leopard coat
that I had talked her out of
before we left the house.
- Oh.
- [sighs]
Hollywood called.
They told me to grab the next flight.
Oh. So you're an actress?
Yes. How did you guess? [chuckles]
[narrator] My mother would often
make unsolicited comments like this.
Good luck in Hollywood.
Thank you.
[inhales deeply, sighs]
[narrator] The terminal was beautiful.
And for some reason,
the hot dog stand was open
even at 4:00 in the morning.
- Hello.
- [narrator] I wanted two.
My mother ordered one.
- [server] We done here?
- [mother] Yes.
Could I have another hot dog?
Do you really, really
want another hot dog?
Yes, I really, really do.
Okay.
["The Best Is Yet to Come" playing]
♪ Out of the tree of life… ♪
[narrator] First class sections
on propeller planes
were usually in the back of the plane,
different from the jets.
First thing I noticed
was the seats were bigger.
Second was the beautiful mural.
♪ Still, it's a real good bet ♪
♪ The best is yet to come ♪
[sighs]
♪ And, babe, won't it be fine? ♪
[engines roaring]
♪ You think you've seen the sun
But you ain't seen it shine ♪
[narrator] When we took off,
it was much more quiet.
That's probably the reason
the seating was placed in the back.
In jets, it's quieter up front.
My mother seemed genuinely excited
to be in first class.
You know, if a film studio
was flying me out here,
the Screen Actors Guild would insist
that the studio fly me out this way.
[whispering] It's the rules.
[breathes deeply, sighs]
["Lazy Afternoon" playing]
[narrator] As the plane
continued to fly westward,
I could see the sun was starting to rise.
As we did a small turn to the right,
the sun came through the window
and seemed as if it were dancing
on my mother's face.
Remember, darling, when I was in
Light Up the Sky in summer stock?
And that critic that said that I was
a cross between Crawford and Stanwyck.
A tour de force performance.
[chuckles]
Wasn't that marvelous?
♪ It's a lazy afternoon… ♪
[sighs]
[narrator] As I looked to my right,
I saw these gold, sparkly curtains.
And I wondered what was behind them.
I looked up and down the aisle
for a stewardess.
I saw one standing by the galley.
I motioned to her,
just the way I would have
in school for my teacher.
["The Girl From Ipanema" playing]
♪ Tall and tan and young and lovely ♪
♪ The girl from Ipanema goes walking ♪
♪ And when she passes ♪
♪ Each one she passes goes, "Ah" ♪
Yes? May I help you?
[narrator] The voice seemed so familiar.
She sounded just like the voice
I'd heard at the terminal in New York.
She looked exactly how I imagined
that person would look.
What's that thing for?
Oh.
That's the sleeper service for
the cross-country overnight flights.
We don't really use them anymore.
When did you use them? What year?
How come you stopped using them?
How many are there?
How about I answer one question at a time?
Okay.
Well, from the time
when this plane was new,
until the jets came in in 1959,
this was used on longer nonstop flights.
Anytime the plane flew,
let's say, over eight hours.
Let's say on an overnight flight
cross-country.
They would sleep people.
It was part of the first-class airfare.
Oh, cool.
How come you know so much?
Well, my mother's been in
the airline industry for years,
originally as a stewardess in the '30s.
Wow.
And she retired in 1939,
but ever since then
she's been doing the flight announcements
at New York Airports.
- [oven bell dings]
- I'll be right back.
You're kidding. Really?
How old is she now?
What kind of planes did she fly in?
Where does she say those announcements
from in the airport?
Well, she's 58 and she mainly
flew in DC-3 planes.
And I think that she does it in a little
room in the back of the TWA terminal.
You have a lot of questions.
You really like flying, don't you?
Is this your first time?
[narrator] Doris answered
all my questions and more.
She was my new best friend.
Mom! Mom! Wake up!
You gotta wake up!
- What is it?
- You're not gonna believe it.
Doris's mother is
the voice at Idlewild Airport.
She's 58 years old and she was
one of the first stewardesses ever.
Mom, you're gonna love her.
She has no accent at all
and she's really beautiful.
- Who?
- Doris!
Oh, that's wonderful, my baby boy.
Mom, don't call me that
in front of Doris, okay?
Okay, darling.
Now let me go back to sleep.
[narrator] Her hair was done
in just the style I liked.
Light eyes.
I couldn't stop looking at her.
How old are you?
Twenty-one.
[Jeff] What's your favorite airplane?
[clicks tongue] Boeing 707.
- Why?
- Because it's beautiful and very fast.
That's pretty good.
Do you have a boyfriend?
I did. But we just broke up.
My mother's an actress, you know?
Really?
[narrator] I used this line
whenever I wanted to impress someone.
That's very interesting.
Yes, we're going to Hollywood.
They called her.
She has to do some movie
with Paul Newman, I think.
Paul Newman, really?
Oh, I can't believe it.
Well, I have to go now.
My mother wanted something.
Okay.
[narrator] Oh, God. Why did I lie?
That was so stupid.
She was already impressed
with just the actress stuff.
[engines roaring]
[narrator] Kansas City Airport
was not very interesting.
Except for this toy store.
Oh, my God. Oh, my God.
There's a battery-operated toy replica
of almost the same airplane we're on.
It was the greatest toy
ever made, bar none.
[whirring]
The door opens, passengers disappear,
stewardess appears.
Oh, my God.
The door closes,
the passengers reappear.
The engines start, one at a time.
Oh, my God. It starts to taxi.
[chattering]
Life at this moment was so good
that it was just hard to recover from.
- So it's $12.95. With tax.
- Okay.
Okay, let me write it up.
- Okay. Great.
- [thuds]
- [gasps]
- [stammers] Oh.
[narrator] Until I broke the plane.
[sad music playing]
I didn't stop crying for an hour,
including the time during takeoff
en route to Denver.
This would be our longest leg,
just under four hours,
due to the headwinds.
What's the matter?
[Jeff] My plane broke.
Well, even real planes break, you know?
They do?
[Doris] Yes, of course they do.
[Jeff] Oh.
Well, I didn't know that.
[narrator] Doris telling me that
changed my life forever.
I had always had a problem
with things being less than perfect
for some reason,
especially mechanical things.
And now she had the answer
that I would use until this day.
Real things break too.
Would you like me to make up
the berth so you can get some sleep?
Yes!
Doris, thank you,
but that won't be necessary.
- Mom!
- [Doris] No, really. It's not a problem.
I'll make it up right now.
[narrator] I was so excited
to be in this berth
looking out into the sky from the window.
I-I just couldn't sleep at all.
I wanted to stay put
so I could have some fun,
maybe even eat a meal in here.
- Your son told me that you're an actress.
- Yes.
And I have to say congratulations
on your Paul Newman film.
That's so exciting.
[mother chuckles]
He must have misunderstood.
There's no specific film.
Just a friend who is going to try
and help me out.
He knows that I love
Paul Newman as an actor,
so he must have put the two together.
[narrator] I was mortified,
and I didn't wanna live anymore.
Lunch is almost ready, so I should
probably check if he wants some.
- Thank you, Doris.
- I'll be back.
You're so sweet.
Lunch is almost ready.
I hope you like chicken.
I like fried chicken.
Well, this is just like it. Only better.
Oh, yeah?
It's called chicken cordon bleu.
Can I have another Coke?
Of course. I'll be right back.
[mutters] Okay.
[engines roaring]
[narrator] The man in the seat
I approximated to be 7D
was drinking a lot and smoking Pall Malls,
a very strong unfiltered cigarette,
my mother told me.
Newports were not nearly as strong.
At any rate, he kept referring
to the headline on the front
of what appeared to be
The Kansas City Star.
It said, "Disaster: Jet Airliner
Crashes at Idlewild."
And below was some blurry,
black-and-white photo.
Air crashes, when I was younger,
were more intriguing to me than upsetting.
I think it was just too much to comprehend
that something I loved so much
could ever hurt anybody,
let alone kill them.
Then I overheard him talking to
a different stewardess, not Doris.
Sir, are you all right?
[inhales deeply] Actually, no.
Um, this is a rough thing to read
because not that long ago,
I… [smacks lips] …booked a trip
from Chicago to New York for business,
and I… I couldn't get on my flight.
I fought for my seat,
but they would not accommodate me.
I went home quite upset,
but by the time I got to the house
and turned the TV on,
I had seen that my plane had crashed.
[whispers] The one I was booked on.
Hmm.
So, I'm… I'm… quite afraid to fly.
I'm so sorry to hear that.
But I can assure you
that nothing will happen and we're fine.
And if you need me, I'm right here.
[breathes shakily] Okay. Good to know.
[sighs]
[narrator] I guess he had
a right to be scared.
Besides, how could I help him
feel any better?
My plane was broken.
It would probably scare him
just to look at it.
And then I had the greatest idea.
Maybe the captain could fix it.
My toy, that is.
Are you married?
No, I'm not actually.
Freshly divorced.
Isn't that a coincidence?
My mother's an actress.
[narrator] I don't think I knew
what a coincidence was.
[sighs] He fixed it.
God, he's the greatest.
Why couldn't he marry my mother?
Thank you!
You know, my mother
is going to be in a movie with,
I think she said,
Kirk Douglas and Elizabeth Taylor.
And Paul Newman.
Really? Paul Newman?
- You don't say.
- Well, I have to go now.
Thank you.
Hi, darling.
- The captain fixed the plane.
- [gasps]
- He's so cool.
- Oh, good.
I'm so happy for you, baby.
[narrator] She looked really pleased,
and I knew why.
Fresh linen had been placed before her,
and the most beautiful china
and silverware for her to look at.
[mother clicks tongue] Oh, my.
Lenox. [chuckles]
It's ill-mannered to turn a plate over
in front of people.
[narrator] My mom loved antiques
and expensive china.
She started to read aloud
the menu, a habit she had.
It was done in a very deep,
theatrical voice
that always embarrassed me at restaurants.
"Your choice of appetizer: shrimp cocktail
or stuffed mushrooms with crab meat.
For the main course, beef with au jus
- or chicken cordon bleu."
- Chicken cordon bleu.
Ugh.
[mother sighing]
["The Good Life" playing]
[narrator] I climbed back up
into my little haven,
my own private world.
♪ Oh, the good life ♪
♪ Full of fun
Seems to be the ideal ♪
Thank you.
♪ Mmm, the good life ♪
♪ Lets you hide
All the sadness you feel… ♪
[narrator] As I looked down
where my mother was sitting,
I wondered what we would do
this year for my birthday.
I started to giggle at the thought of
when I was little, my fifth birthday.
It was so successful
that I wanted a party every day.
My mother gave in for about five days.
And then I had to learn the ugly truth,
birthdays lasted only one day, usually.
But no one told me that I couldn't
have them every month.
I can remember that one time in April
my mother's friend walked in
on one of my birthdays and said,
"Isn't his birthday in February?"
"Yes," my mother said,
"but don't spoil it for him."
My mother was good that way.
- Thank you.
- You're welcome.
[narrator] I laid down on my side.
The drone of the engines seemed
to be kind of lulling me.
Before I knew it, I was asleep.
For many years to come,
I would scrounge through
my airline schedules
to find a propeller plane to fly,
providing that I had the time,
just so I could get
the same kind of sleep.
♪ And in case you wonder why… ♪
Now, you can stay up here as long as
you're strapped in, okay?
- Okay.
This is your captain speaking.
We are expecting moderate turbulence
for the next 20 minutes.
Please remain seated
and, uh, fasten your seat belts.
[narrator] The aircraft started
to buffet and rumble a bit.
The pitch of the engine sound changed
as we started to climb above the weather.
However, the turbulence got worse,
and some of the passengers
started to look around
as if maybe something they could
look at would solve this problem.
The man in 12A got up
and strangely moved toward
the back of the plane.
[stewardess] You okay?
He yelled out to no one.
Stop following me!
Sir? Sir, can I help you?
[narrator] The stewardess
that I didn't know ran after him.
- Sir, can I help you? That's okay.
- What a bizarre sight.
The man had his hands around
the throat of the young lady,
and she had her hands
around his throat as well.
There seemed to be a genuine
resistance between the two.
I understand. I've been there.
But they were having quite
a normal conversation.
There's more to this character
than meets the eye.
- There's a problem.
- Breathe out.
- Thank you.
- [both exhale]
[narrator] When he boarded
before everyone else did,
apparently he was drugged
and placed on board
so he could be transferred to
a different mental hospital in Denver.
- [stewardess] Oh, thank you so much.
- [pilot speaks indistinctly]
[stewardess]
If you need anything, let me know.
[narrator] They were talking
in such a calm manner.
It was hard to believe anything was wrong.
And together they managed
to calm him down.
Still everyone was quite uneasy
until we disembarked.
- Let's get you to sit down, okay?
- Yeah, I'm okay.
[engines roaring]
- Good luck on that Paul Newman film.
- [chuckles]
Why, thank you.
I'll need it.
[chuckles]
Why do you think our plane broke down?
[clicks tongue] I don't know, darling,
but it's okay.
It will give us a good night's sleep.
And tomorrow we will
have a wonderful flight.
[clicks tongue]
And what do you say
we read a play together?
I think we should read
The Philadelphia Story.
- All right.
- Okay.
[narrator]
Actually, staying in Denver was fun.
That night, Mom read two acts of a play.
Ever since I can remember,
Mom read me good-night plays
instead of fairy tales.
We went to lunch
at the Denver terminal restaurant.
Grilled cheese and a Coke
as I watched the airplanes come and go.
This was just great.
What could happen to beat everything
that's happened so far?
Nothing.
I wanted to live forever.
- Enjoy your flight.
- Thank you. Have a nice flight.
Hi, there's a note in there
for you to read.
Yes, Liz told me all about it.
Wait! We're at the wrong gate!
Mom, we're gonna miss the plane!
It's not this one, Mom. I'm telling you!
This is a nonstop jet flight to LA.
I know it by heart.
StarStream Boeing 707
Royal Ambassador service.
- Thank you. I'll take that for him.
- Enjoy your flight.
Thank you.
Surprise, honey.
We are going on a jet.
- What?
- [chuckles]
[stutters] I can't believe it.
We're taking the 707 to LA.
Aren't you excited, honey?
This is your surprise from Liz.
What's wrong, baby?
Nothing, i-it's just…
Well, we're going to get on there
and you're gonna start showing off.
[mother clicks tongue]
[mother] Well,
let's just head to the gate, okay?
[narrator] I was excited, truly.
But sometimes I just didn't know
how to express it.
Somehow I felt a kind of loss.
Maybe it was saying goodbye
to that big, beautiful old Connie,
or maybe it was never seeing Doris again.
She didn't say anything,
and I felt really bad.
[triumphant music playing]
[narrator] There it was.
An absolute specimen of an aircraft.
It was art. Believe me, it was art.
[no audible dialogue]
I was on a jet and in first class.
I just couldn't believe it.
My mother said I could sit by myself
so I could pretend
that I was flying alone.
She decided to sit
by a lovely woman named Barbara.
[engines roaring]
[narrator] A surge of power
thrust me back in the seat.
Wow. Fantastic.
[narrator] And it was fantastic.
Straight up into the air we went.
We were over the Colorado mountains
before we knew it.
The snowcapped mountains glistening
in the afternoon light were unforgettable.
We leveled off,
and the captain came over the speaker.
[captain] Ladies and gentlemen,
welcome to the jet age.
We are flying at 600 miles an hour
at an altitude of 33,000 feet.
Our flying time to Los Angeles
will be one hour and 52 minutes.
So sit back and enjoy your flight.
- Champagne is on me.
- [both chuckle]
[mother sighs]
[narrator]
Barbara was a little older than my mom,
but very pretty
and just like my mother liked,
sophisticated, wealthy and no accent.
[Barbara] No, no.
Unfortunately, my husband
passed away many years ago.
- Oh. [click tongue]
- Henry was his name and…
Oh, I'll tell you the story.
He was at a podium accepting
the presidency for the Crocker Bank
- when he had a massive heart attack.
- Oh, my God.
- Oh, Barbara.
- Forty-three years old.
[narrator] I decided to roam the cabin.
I was walking in a very cocky manner.
A way that only an eight-year-old could do
when he knows he's doing
something truly special.
As I looked to the left, down the aisle,
I saw a young kid there.
He was younger than me.
About two years I'd say.
He sat with an official airline guide,
or OAG,
which only travel agents
in big companies have.
Is that the latest OAG?
My dad gets 'em in the mail
before anybody does.
Geez, you're so lucky.
I'll be right back.
Mom, I made a new best friend!
- He has an OAG. Oh, my gosh--
- Oh, Jeff, darling.
Jeff, this is Barbara.
And believe it or not,
her father owns an airline.
- Trans Caribbean Airlines.
- Mm-hmm.
- Really?
- [Barbara] Yeah.
And I'll have you know that my father
put my name, Barbara,
on the nose of a brand-new DC-8 jetliner.
- Wow. That's so cool.
- [Barbara] Mm-hmm.
[narrator] A plane with her name on it.
Do I stay here or go back
to my new best friend, Skipper?
- Kids.
- [both chuckle]
[narrator] The next hour
was filled with conversation
that only would fascinate
Skipper and myself.
Can you believe that TWA
had a nonstop flight
from London to San Francisco
that took 22 hours right up to 1960?
Wow, really?
[narrator]
None of my friends are into aviation,
but now I have Skipper.
- Where's your father?
- Over there.
[Jeff] What does he do?
- He's a lawyer.
- [Jeff] Where's your mother?
Oh, she died when I was three.
Oh, really? Do you have a new mother?
No, my dad remarried twice
after my mom died,
and they died of cancer too.
- All of them.
- You're kidding.
Does he have an accent?
I don't know. Does it matter?
Well, kinda.
I don't think he does.
Oh, great. My mom's gonna love him.
She loves people without accents.
- To Hollywood. [chuckles]
- [chuckles]
- To us.
- Yes.
- I still can't believe--
- Mom!
I made this new best friend,
and his dad is rich and sad
and has no accent.
[both laugh]
Well, make sure you tell him
which row I'm in.
[chuckles]
Hi.
Why are you here?
Well, I changed my flight
so I could see you guys one last time.
[narrator] I'll never wash my face again.
This is too good.
My girlfriend, my buddy,
my mom's new husband, hopefully.
And we're all on a new jet
heading westward.
It's scientifically impossible
for life to be any better.
[engines roaring]
Hello. Would you care
for some chateaubriand?
- No.
Do you like chicken?
Not really.
You don't like fried chicken?
I love fried chicken.
Well, this is just like it.
It's called chicken cordon bleu.
But on our jet flights,
we also offer a children's menu,
which is your choice
of hot dog, hamburger,
and peanut butter and jelly sandwich.
I'll have a hot dog with mustard.
I'll have a hot dog
with no mustard, no ketchup.
Perfect.
[narrator] I thought I would faint.
A hot dog at 35,000 feet?
I was so excited I-I was lost for words.
But I had to say something,
so I turned to Skip.
I like your official airline guidebook.
Thanks.
[narrator] The sun was shining,
the sky was brilliant blue,
and I was eating a hot dog
and drinking a Coke
with my new best friend
at 600 miles an hour.
From that moment on,
I never thought things could get better.
["Un Homme Et Une Femme" playing]
[chattering]
[engines roaring]
[narrator] As we taxied in,
I could see the new
space-age-style restaurant at LAX.
It was truly beautiful.
I'd really like to eat there
sometime, I thought.
["Aujourd'hui, c'est toi" playing]
Through the window,
I could see the jetway
start to glide over to meet our plane.
Mom, there's movie cameras out there.
- You're kidding.
- No, he's not.
- Better safe than sorry.
- Yeah.
Well, you look wonderful.
[dramatic music playing]
[no audible dialogue]
What are all those cameras
doing out there?
[narrator] It was the captain of our jet.
He was 62 years old,
and this was his last flight.
[captain] Doris told me all about you.
- Is your name Jeff?
- Yeah.
[captain] How would you like
to walk the jetway with me?
[narrator] And Life Magazine
was doing a TV special on him.
Okay, I've got one last question.
What are you gonna do
now that you're retired?
Well, I haven't officially retired
until I sign out,
but, uh, if you're gonna make me retire
in front of your cameras…
I think that, uh… [sighs]
…I think that I would like
to give my wings
to this young man
who I think…
has flying in his blood.
[lighthearted music playing]
[narrator] I took that moment
in my life so seriously
that today I'm a captain myself.
And I married Doris,
although I had some catching up to do.
Thirteen years to be exact.
But nevertheless, happily married.
An aviation couple to the max.
As a matter of fact,
I get to see her almost every day.
She's the new voice at JFK,
and I've got the New York, LA run.
Very convenient.
Oh, yeah.
In case you're wondering about my mom,
she never married Skipper's dad,
but she did get to date him for a while.
We all pretended that it would work out.
She's very happy though.
She teaches acting
at the Pasadena Playhouse in California.
She's 80 now and gets a big kick
out of the young guys.
And Liz is her favorite student,
has been for almost 20 years.
It's been a wonderful life.